A Guide to the Institute of International Education records, Publications, Microforms, RG 3, Series 2 FA1315
Rockefeller Archive Center
Institute of International Education records, Publications, Microforms, RG 3, Series 2
1919-1989
Rockefeller Archive Center
Institute of International Education (New York, N.Y.)
FA1315
106 microform reels 106 microform reels including duplicates.
106 16mm reels of microfilm including 38 reels of unique content and duplicate reels.
Arrangement
Records are arranged as received.
Biographical / Historical
The Institute of International Education (IIE) was established in 1919 by Nobel Prize winners Nicholas Murray Butler, Elihu Root and Stephen Duggan, Sr. The founders sought greater understanding among nations, primarily through the establishment of international educational exchange between United States institutes of higher education and foreign actors interested in formulating and developing active and ongoing educational understanding. As the Institute grew, developed and matured, it has continued to focus in the area of scholars exchange, as well as education services, international development and leadership training.
IIE initially focused on facilitating student, faculty, and teacher exchanges with European countries. In the 1930s their scope expanded beyond Europe to include exchanges between the Soviet Union and Latin America. During this period the Institute also established the Emergency Committee to Aid Displaced German Scholars which later expanded to include scholars fleeing facist Spain and Italy as well. In the 1950s this program was utilized to support Hungarian refugees. In the early 2000s IIE Trustees together with other donors endowed the Scholar Rescue Fund (SRF).
Following WWII, the Institute helped establish the Association of International Educators (NAFSA) and the Council on International Education Exchange (CIEE) for which they serve to administer the CIEE faculty component and the graduate student component of the Fullbright program, which continues to today as the Institute's largest program.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Records were transferred to RAC by the Institute of International Education through several accessions in 2017.
Related Materials
The Council for International Exchange of Scholars (CIES) collection is available at the University of Arkansas.
The Emergency Committee in Aid of Displaced Foreign Scholars records are available at the New York Public Library.
The International Fellowship Fund (IFF) Archives are available at Columbia University.
Other Finding Aids
Institute of International Education records are available in the following other finding aids:
Institute of International Education records, Alumni and Historical Files, RG 1 (FA1289)
Institute of International Education records, Fellowship Cards (Grantee Locator Cards), RG 2 (FA1290)
Institute of International Education records, Publications, Paper records, RG 3, Series 1 (FA1291)
Institute of International Education records, Photographic Files, RG 4 (FA1288)
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Scope and Contents
Contains publications produced by the Institute of International Education (IIE), publications produced by IIE in partnership with others, as well as publications collected by IIE that were produced by other foundations, institutions and government agencies. Contents include: reports, pamphlets, surveys, conference proceedings, policy papers, a selection of IIE Annual Reports and Bulletins. Much of the material is guides for foreign students studying in the United States, U.S. students studying abroad as well as guides for foreign students returning home following the completion of their residencies in the United States. Records may or may not duplicate those found in "Publications, Paper records, RG 3, Series 1" (FA1291).
- Publications - Microforms, 1919-1989; 2
  - Annual Reports, 1920-1953 (Reel 1-C8)
  - Annual Reports, 1953-1984 (Reel 2-C9)
  - Annual Reports, 1964-1968 (Reel 3-C10)
  - Institute Bulletins, 1920-1931 (Reel 3-C10)
  - Institute Bulletins, 1931-1953 (Reel 4-C11)
  - Institute Bulletins, 1954-1956 (Reel 5-C12)
  - News Bulletins, 1920-1942 (Reel 5-C12)
  - News Bulletins, 1942-1950 (Reel 6-C13)
  - News Bulletins, 1950-1954 (Reel 7-C14)
  - News Bulletins, 1953-1959 (Reel 8-C15)
  - New Bulletins and Overseas Magazine, 1958-1964 (Reel 9-C16)
  - Study Abroad Information; Handbooks on International Study, 1955-1972 (Reel 10-C17)
  - Handbooks for International Study; Handbook-Study in American Republics; Handbook-Study in Europe; Undergraduate Study Abroad, 1961-1973 (Reel 11-C18)
  - Handbook on International Study: For U.S. Nationals, 1965 (Reel 11-C18)
  - Handbook on International Study: For U.S. Nationals, 1961 (Reel 11-C18)
  - Handbook on International Study: For Foreign Nationals, 1961 (Reel 11-C18)
  - Handbook on International Study: For U.S. Nationals, 1971 (Reel 11-C18)
  - Handbook on International Study: For Foreign Nationals, 1971 (Reel 11-C18)
  - Handbook on International Study: For Foreign Nationals, 1973 (Reel 11-C18)
  - Handbook - Study in American Republics Area (Reel 11-C18)
  - Handbook - Study in Europe Undergraduate Study Abroad (Reel 11-C18)
  - U.S. College Sponsored Programs Abroad, 1973-1982 (Reel 12-C19)
  - The Learning Year Aboard, Vol. 1, 1983 (Reel 12-C19)
  - Academic Year Aboard, 1986-1987 (Reel 12-C19)
  - Academic Year Aboard, 1986-1987 (Reel 13-C20)
  - Summer Study Aboard, 1977-1978 (Reel 13-C20)
  - Learning Travel, Vacation Study Abroard, 1980-1987 (Reel 14-C21)
  - Teaching Abroad, 1973; 1976 (Reel 14-C21)
  - Meet the USA, 1970 (Reel 14-C21)
  - Meet the USA, 1947-1952; 1959; 1970 (Reel 15-C26A-27)
  - English Language Orientation Program in the USA, 1982; 1984 (Reel 15-C26A-27)
  - Study of Agriculture in the USA, 1971 (Reel 16-C28)
  - Teacher Education in the USA, 1971 (Reel 16-C28)
  - Teacher Education Preparation Institution in the U.S., 1962 September (Reel 16-C28)
  - Fields of Study, 1979 (Reel 16-C28)
  - The Community Technical College in the U.S., 1978 (Reel 16-C28)
  - The Two Year College in the U.S., 1967 (Reel 16-C28)
  - English Language Orientation Program in the USA, 1969; 1973; 1978; 1980 (Reel 16-C28)
  - Summer Learning Options USA, 1964; 1983 (Reel 16-C28)
  - Specialized Study Options USA, 1984; 1986-1988 (Reel 16-C28)
  - Summer Programs in the USA, 1977 (Reel 16-C28)
  - Study in U.S. Colleges and Universities, 1983 (Reel 16-C28)
  - Engineering Education in USA, 1973 (Reel 16-C28)
  - Undergraduate Study in U.S., 1973 (Reel 17-C29)
  - Graduate Study in U.S., 1953; 1967-1972 (Reel 17-C29)
  - Practical Guide for Foreign Visitors, 1976 (Reel 17-C29)
  - Basic Facts on Foreign Study, 1973; 1985 (Reel 17-C29)
  - Guide to Foreign Medical Schools, 1973-1975 (Reel 17-C29)
  - Planning for Study Abroad, 1964 (Reel 17-C29)
  - Study in Mexico, 1973 (Reel 17-C29)
  - The Population Involved in International Education (Reel 17-C29)
  - Foreign Student Census, 1948-1952 (Reel 17-C29)
  - Education for One World, 1953-1954 (Reel 17-C29)
  - Open Doors, 1954-1977 (Reel 17-C29)
  - Open Doors, 1977-1985 (Reel 18-C30)
  - Profiles - The Foreign Student in U.S., 1981; 1983 (Reel 18-C30)
  - Living Costs Tuition and Fee Charges, 1973 (Reel 18-C30)
  - Costs at U.S. Educational Institutions, 1980-1986 (Reel 19-C31)
  - Change through International Education (Reel A-1)
  - National Development and the Universities (Reel A-1)
  - El Desarrollo (Reel A-1)
  - Las Artes (Reel A-1)
  - The Arts and the Universities (Reel A-1)
  - Clear, 1961 May (Reel A-1)
  - Catalyst for Inter-American Higher Education (Reel A-1)
  - Educational Needs of Latin America (Reel A-1)
  - La Agriculturia (Reel A-1)
  - TOMO II (Reel A-1)
  - Agriculture and the Universities (Reel A-1)
  - Higher Education in Argentina (Reel A-1)
  - Educational Exchange for Dev Nations, 1980 (Reel A-2)
  - Third National Conference on Exchange of Persons, 1959 (Reel A-2)
  - International Education Trends 2000, 1979 (Reel A-2)
  - Curriculum-U.S. Capacities - Dev Needs, 1979 (Reel A-2)
  - Report 50th Anniversary Conference Series Closing Dinner, 1970 (Reel A-2)
  - IIE at 50th Intl Ed - Resources in the 70s (Reel A-2)
  - Closing the Worldwide Learning Gap (Reel A-2)
  - International Education - Resources and Responsibilities, 1969 (Reel A-2)
  - Fifth Conference on International Education, 1964 (Reel A-2)
  - National Development through International Education, 1964 (Reel A-2)
  - Overseas (Reel A-2)
  - IIE Fourth National Conference, 1960 (Reel A-2)
  - Report to the President of the United States (Reel A-2)
  - Third National Conference on Exchange of Persons, 1959 (Reel A-2)
  - World Progress through Education Exchange, 1959 (Reel A-2)
  - Recommendations Second National Conference on Exchange of Persons, 1956 (Reel A-2)
  - Education for International Responsibility Second National Conference, 1956 (Reel A-2)
  - To Strenghten World Freedom (Reel A-2)
  - Report of National Conference, 1955 (Reel A-2)
  - Regional Education - Asia (Reel A-2)
  - Admin to American Colleges and Universities (Reel A-2)
  - IIE Scholarship - Hong Kong, 1966-1977 (Reel A-2)
  - IIE in Houston (Reel A-2)
  - Annual Report, Houston, 1957-1958 (Reel A-2)
  - Annual Report, Houston, 1964-1965 (Reel A-2)
  - Canadian Festival, 1978 (Reel A-2)
  - Foreign Students Guide to Chicago (Reel A-2)
  - Press Releases, 1971 September (Reel A-2)
  - Second National Conference on Exchange of Persons (Reel A-3)
  - News Releases, 1957 April-1962 September (Reel A-4)
  - Various U.S. and Foreign Grant Booklets, 62-70, 72-72-74, 76-81, 84 (Reel A-5)
  - Fullbright Booklets (Reel A-5)
  - ITT Grants, 1974-1988 (Reel A-5)
  - GMA Tech Asst., 1978 September (Reel A-5)
  - Grammarishal de Ayacuilto Program (Reel A-5)
  - IIE Foreign Lectures, 1919-1929 (Reel A-5)
  - IIE Special Reports, 1949-1959 (Reel A-5)
  - Study Abroard Summer 1967 (Reel A-6)
  - Handbook on International Study, 1955; 1958; 1970-1975 (Reel A-6)
  - Handbook on International Study, 1975 (Reel A-7)
  - Handbook on International Study: For U.S. Nationals, 1961 (Reel A-7)
  - Handbook on International Study: For Foreign Nationals, 1961 (Reel A-7)
  - Handbook on International Study: For Foreign Nationals, 1965 (Reel A-7)
  - Study in Americas, 1976 (Reel A-7)
  - Undergrad Study Abroad, 1964-1965 (Reel A-7)
  - Study in Europe, 1976 (Reel A-7)
  - Academic Year Abroad, 1988-1989 (Reel A-7)
  - Vacation Study Abroad, 1988 (Reel A-7)
  - Vacation Study Abroad, 1988 (Reel A-8)
  - Basic Facts, 1987 (Reel A-8)
  - Mentors and Supervisors, 1987 (Reel A-8)
  - U.S. Study Abroad, 1988 (Reel A-8)
  - Abroad and Beyond, 1988 (Reel A-8)
  - Foreign Students in Region Econ, 1988 (Reel A-8)
  - Teaching Abroad (Reel A-8)
  - Profiles, 1985-1986 (Reel A-8)
  - Open Doors, 1986-1987 (Reel A-8)
  - U.S. College Expand to South Africa, 1987 (Reel A-8)
  - Regional Education - Asia (Reel A-8)
  - Regional Education - Central America (Reel A-8)
  - IIE Annual Report - West Coast, Southeast, Rocky Mountains, Mid-West, 1987 (Reel A-8)
  - ART, 1955-1987 (Reel A-8)
  - Meet the USA, 1947-1952; 1959; 1971; 1975 (Reel A-9)
  - Meet the USA (in various languages), 1965 (Reel A-9)
  - Meet the USA (in various languages) (Reel A-10)
  - English Language and Orientation in U.S., 1969; 1973; 1976; 1978; 1980 (Reel A-10)
  - Specialized Study Options USA (Reel A-10)
  - Specialized Study Options USA, 1986-1987 (Reel A-11)
  - English Language Orientation, 1964 (Reel A-11)
  - Summer Learning Options, 1983 (Reel A-11)
  - Guide to Foreign Medical Schools (Reel A-11)
  - Study in Mexico (Reel A-11)
  - Planning for Study Abroad (Reel A-11)
  - Undergrad in U.S. - the Four-Year College (Reel A-11)
  - Grads in U.S. (Reel A-11)
  - Guide for Foreign Students - Visitors (Reel A-11)
  - Basic Facts on Foreign Studies (Reel A-11)
  - Two Year Colleges in U.S. - Land Grant College Admissions in U.S. (Reel A-11)
  - Two Year Colleges in U.S. - The Community, Tech and Junior Colleges (Reel A-11)
  - Fields of Study in U.S. (Reel A-11)
  - Teacher Prep in U.S. - Teacher Education (Reel A-11)
  - Study of Agriculture, Eng, in U.S. (Reel A-11)
  - Study in U.S. - Summer Program in U.S. (Reel A-11)
  - International Relations Clubs, 1920-1923 (Reel A-11)
  - American Field Scholarships, 1919-1938 (Reel A-11)
  - IIE Research Reports - 13 - International Exchange Off Campus (Reel A-12)
  - IIE Research Reports - 12 - The Foreign Student Factor (Reel A-12)
  - IIE Research Reports - 9 - Decline and Renewal (Reel A-12)
  - IIE Research Reports - 10 - Choosing Schools from Afar (Reel A-12)
  - IIE Research Reports - 11 - Economics of Foreign Students (Reel A-12)
  - IIE Research Reports - 7 - Foreign Student Flow (Reel A-12)
  - IIE Research Reports - 5 - Fondness and Frustration (Reel A-12)
  - IIE Research Reports - 4 - International Fellowships (Reel A-12)
  - IIE Research Reports - 3 - Survey of Policy Change (Reel A-12)
  - Black Education in S. Africa (Reel A-12)
  - Absence of Decision - Conference Reports, 1946-1955 (Reel A-12)
  - Undergrads, Graduates Overseas, 1966 (Reel A-12)
  - Transplanted Students, 1961 (Reel A-12)
  - Academic Progress Abroad, 1960 (Reel A-12)
  - Foreign Studies for U.S. Undergrads, 1958 (Reel A-12)
  - Cultural Attitudes and Understanding, 1953 (Reel A-12)
  - Academic Orientation - Foreign Grads, 1967 (Reel A-12)
  - Program for U.S. Undergrads, 1960 (Reel A-12)
  - Problems in Medical Training, 1953 (Reel A-12)
  - Pase VI Reports (Reel A-12)
  - Admissions - Workshop, 1964 (Reel A-12)
  - Admissions - Col. Policies, 1965 (Reel A-12)
  - Admissions - Workshop, 1964 (Reel A-12)
  - Admissions - Placement, 1962 (Reel A-12)
  - Admissions - Policy, 1955 (Reel A-12)
  - Export of Tech Education, 1968 (Reel A-12)
  - Study Coop Arab, 1977 (Reel A-12)
  - Syrian Study Abroad, 1952-1953 (Reel A-13)
  - Placement of Mid-East and North Africans, 1966 (Reel A-13)
  - Amer. University Union in Europe, 1919-1929 (Reel A-13)
  - IIE Seminar - Ind. Tech in USSR, 1960 (Reel A-13)
  - Change through Interchange, 1958 (Reel A-13)
  - Inter-Amer. Study of S. America Student, 1942 (Reel A-13)
  - IIE Seminar on Education in USSR, 1959 (Reel A-13)
  - IIE Seminar on Art, 1960 (Reel A-13)
  - IIE Seminar on Agriculture, 1960 (Reel A-13)
  - Study of USSR, 1959 (Reel A-13)
  - Higher Education Reform, 1978 (Reel A-13)
  - US Study Prog - W. Germany Ed Inst., 1969 (Reel A-13)
  - Guide - Admission Taiwan and Hong Kong, 1966 (Reel A-13)
  - Cooperation Between Japanese and American Law Schools, 1953 (Reel A-13)
  - Note on India, 1852 (Reel A-13)
  - Japanese Leadership Program, 1950-1951 (Reel A-13)
  - Orientation - Japanese and Ryukyuan Students, 1950 (Reel A-13)
  - Higher Education in Sudan, 1977 (Reel A-13)
  - African Students, 1961 (Reel A-13)
  - Educ. Exchange in Atlantic Area, 1965 (Reel A-13)
  - IIE Survey of African Students, 1961 (Reel A-13)
  - Military Asst. Train Program, 1964 (Reel A-14)
  - Women in Educ. Exchange in Dev. Countries, 1963 (Reel A-14)
  - Foreign Professors in U.S. Colleges, 1963 (Reel A-14)
  - Foreign Student Ex. In Eco. Dev. Nations, 1961 (Reel A-14)
  - African Students in the U.S., 1960 (Reel A-14)
  - International Youth Service, 1960 (Reel A-14)
  - S. America and Southeast Asia Update, 1982 (Reel A-14)
  - IIE Reports, 1966-1974 (Reel A-14)
  - Exchange Newsletters, 1953-1955 (Reel A-14)
  - Secretariat News, 1957-1962 (Reel A-14)
  - Undergrad Overseas, 1966 (Reel A-14)
  - Transplanted Students, 1961 (Reel A-14)
  - Academic Programs Abroad, 1960 (Reel A-14)
  - Foreign Study for U.S. Undergrads, 1958 (Reel A-14)
  - Cultural Attitudes, 1953 (Reel A-14)
  - Program for U.S. Undergrads, 1960 (Reel A-14)
  - Research in Program for Foreign Students, 1969 (Reel A-14)
  - Academic Orientation - Foreign Grads, 1967 (Reel A-14)
  - AID, IIE, VISTA Summer 1967 (Reel A-14)
  - Workshop on Admissions, 1964 (Reel A-14)
  - Problems Associated with Grad Medical Training in U.S. (Reel A-14)
  - Guide to Admissions, 1962 (Reel A-14)
  - Export of Tech Education, 1968 (Reel A-14)
  - Change through Interchange, 1958 (Reel A-14)
  - Gran Mariscal de Ayacucho Program, 1974-1977 (Reel A-14)
  - Higher Education Reform, 1978 (Reel A-14)
  - Higher Education Reform, 1978 (Reel A-15)
  - IIE Seminar on Ind. Tech in USSR, 1960 (Reel A-15)
  - IIE Seminar on Education in USSR, 1959 (Reel A-15)
  - IIE Seminar on Arts, 1960 (Reel A-15)
  - IIE Seminar on Agriculture, 1960 (Reel A-15)
  - Study Prog-West Germany Ed. Inst., 1969 (Reel A-15)
  - Note on Relation Ec. Dev. And Ind. In India, 1952 (Reel A-15)
  - Japanese Leadership Program, 1950-1951 (Reel A-15)
  - Admissions Guidelines Mid East and N. Africa (Reel A-15)
  - Syrian Students Abroad, 1952 (Reel A-15)
  - Coop. in Arab Countries and Iran, 1977 (Reel A-15)
  - Higher Education in Sudan, 1977 (Reel A-15)
  - African Students, 1961-1962 (Reel A-15)
  - IIE Special Publications, 1949-1959 (Reel A-15)
  - Miscellaneous Publications, 1920-1950 (Reel A-16)
  - IIE S. Halpern, 1969 (Reel A-16)
  - The Communist Conspiracy, 1956 (Reel A-16)
  - Extramural Lectures Report No. 1 (Reel A-16)
  - IIE 1919-1944 (Reel A-16)
  - Open Doors to Open Minds 1919-1969 (Reel A-16)
  - IIE 1919-1969 (Reel A-16)
  - Briefing Background 1969: Haiti, Honduras, Jamaica, Nicaragua, Trinidad and Tobago, Paraguay, Panama (Reel A-16)
  - IIE Recommendations for Ex. Improv., 1965 (Reel A-16)
  - Report on Fullbright-Hays, 1967 (Reel A-16)
  - 30 Years with Fullbright (Reel A-16)
  - Fullbright Ex through IIE (Reel A-16)
  - U.S. Government Grants, 1950-1956 (Reel A-16)
  - Grants with Ireland, 1959-1960 (Reel A-16)
  - Grants to American Students, 1958-1959 (Reel A-16)
  - Bibliographies: Study in U.S. Colleges, 1979 (Reel A-17)
  - Higher Education, World View, Higher Education Abroad, 1979 (Reel A-17)
  - International Education Exchange, 1971 (Reel A-17)
  - Research in International Education, 1960-1969 (Reel A-17)
  - Survey, 1960-1961 (Reel A-17)
  - Education is Development and Development is Education, 1975 (Reel A-17)
  - Andean Common Market, 1975 (Reel A-17)
  - Changing Role of Ed. Coop. in Asia, 1975 (Reel A-17)
  - Collaboration in Science and Technology, 1975 (Reel A-17)
  - Evolving Pattern Asian Univer., 1976 (Reel A-17)
  - Alternatives to Training Med. In Latin Am. (Reel A-17)
  - Latin Am. Studies, 1976 (Reel A-17)
  - Equal, Equity or Equilibrium, 1976 (Reel A-17)
  - Higher Education in Asia and U.S., 1972 (Reel A-17)
  - Education and Work, 1979 (Reel A-17)
  - Education and Work, University and Society, 1974 (Reel A-17)
  - Higher Ed. In Latin Am., 1973 (Reel A-17)
  - Comm. Tech and Crisis, 1971 (Reel A-17)
  - Student Act, 1970 (Reel A-17)
  - Education for Journalism in Latin Am., 1970 (Reel A-17)
  - Demography and University, 1969 (Reel A-17)
  - Education Technology, 1969 (Reel A-17)
  - The University in Society (Reel A-17)
  - Release Books, 1963-1965 (Reel A-17)
  - Release Books, 1964 May-1965 May (Reel A-18)
  - Open Door to Open Mind 1919-1969 (Reel A-19)
  - Study of Europe, 1976 (Reel A-19)
  - S. Halpern, 1969 (Reel A-19)
  - Statement of Comm. On Ed. Interchange Policy, 1955-1960 (Reel A-19)
  - Geographic Distribution in Exchange Programs, 1956 (Reel A-19)
  - Chinese Students in U.S., 1948-1955 (Reel A-19)
  - Orientation of Foreign Students, 1956 (Reel A-19)
  - Expanding University Enrollment of Foreign Students, 1957 (Reel A-19)
  - Hungarian Refugee Students, 1956-1957 (Reel A-19)
  - U.S. Medical Training for Foreign Students, 1957 (Reel A-19)
  - The Foreign Student: Exchange of Immigrant, 1958 (Reel A-19)
  - Hungarian Refugee Students, 1958 (Reel A-19)
  - Academic Exchange with Soviet Union (Reel A-19)
  - 20 Years of U.S. Programs in Cultural Exchange, 1959 (Reel A-19)
  - College and University Programs of Academic Exchange, 1960 (Reel A-19)
  - Foreign Study for Syrians, 1953 (Reel A-19)
  - African Students, 1961 (Reel A-19)